Wilma Keyes Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Wilma Keyes Papers.
undated, 1926-1972.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Keyes, Wilma.
1.8 linear feet.
Wilma Belknap Keyes was an assistant professor at the University of Connecticut School of Home Economics from 1938-1963. During her tenure she developed and taught over 20 new art courses and saw the beginning of the School of Fine Arts as a distinct department from the School of Home Economics.
MSS19880019
Biography
Wilma Belknap Keyes was born in New Jersey on 15 January 1902, the daughter of John D. and Grace Vrooman Keyes. She was a graduate of M.A.N.Y. University and the New York School of Fine and Applied Art (Parsons). During her early career, she worked for Art Education Press, Inc., and was affiliated with Idaho State University from 1923-1927. She taught at Michigan State University from 1937-1938.
From 1938 to 1963, Wilma Keyes was an assistant professor of Related Arts at the University of Connecticut School of Home Economics. When she arrived at the University of Connecticut only five art courses were being offered. During her tenure she developed and taught over 20 new art courses and saw the beginning of the School of Fine Arts as a distinct department from the School of Home Economics. At the time of her retirement, over 60 courses were being offered in the arts program.
Wilma Keyes was a member of many professional organizations and held honorary positions on the Board of Directors of the Connecticut Arts Association and the Society of Connecticut Craftsmen. She was a member of the American Institute of Interior Designers Association, the National Art Education Association, the American Home Economics Association, the Eastern Arts Association, the Connecticut Arts Association, the Connecticut Historical Society, and Pi Beta Phi.
Miss Keyes is listed in Who's Who in American Education, Who's Who of American Women, and Who's Who in the East.
Scope and Content
Many of the files are useful sources in tracing the development of the fine arts program and its emergence from the School of Home Economics at the University of Connecticut. The oral histories are wonderful recollections of life on the University of Connecticut during the early part of this century.
Arrangement
The Wilma Keyes Papers are arranged in six series:
Series I: Academic Files ( 1938-1961 ) are arranged topical files. This series includes items such as: American Home Economics Association; Annual Report of Home Economics, 1941-61 (gaps); Art Courses; Correspondence; Keyes' cumulative record of professional staff activities; photographs; Report of Committee for the Correlation of Related Arts with Textiles and Clothing, 1938-39; state teaching certificate requirements; Women's Faculty Club. Files pertaining to individual art courses include course descriptions, mid-term and final exam copies and other information. Many of the files are useful sources in tracing the development of the Fine Arts program and its emergence from the School of Home Economics.
Series II: Correspondence and Notes ( undated ) deals specifically with Miss Keyes' research into the Louis Crombie Beach Memorial Collection of Art and President and Mrs. Charles Lewis Beach. There is some correspondence with faculty members from the early 20th century.
Series III: Publications ( undated, 1926-1972 ) deals with either the field of home economics or campus activities at the University of Connecticut. This series is arranged alphabetically by title. It includes publications such as: A History of the Connecticut Home Economics Association; Connecticut Home Economics Newsletter; Dedication of...Home Economics Building...; Fine Arts Magazine; Home Economics News; The Louise Crombie Beach Memorial Collection of Art; Mr. Beach.
Series IV: Scrapbooks ( undated, 1944-1962 ) contains Guest/Scrap books from exhibits 1944-46, and loose scrapbook pages. They are a miscellaneous group of newspaper clippings, programs, notices dealing primarily with exhibitions and lectures at the University of Connecticut School of Home Economics. Of interest is a photograph of Eleanor Roosevelt's visit to the University.
Series V: Tapes and Oral History ( 1970s ) are the taped interviews done in the early 1970s as part of Miss Keyes' research project on the Beach Collection. The oral history project was a joint venture with the William Benton Museum of Art. All the cassette tapes have been transcribed; the transcriptions, following, should be used in lieu of the tapes.
Series VI: Transcripts and Oral History ( 1970s ) is arranged alphabetically by the name of the person being interviewed: Anderson, Helen Stevens and Winifred Smith Passmore; Belden, Robert Fitch; Brundage, Mrs. A.J. and Mrs. I.G. Davis; Fultz, Charlotte Dutch; Griswold, Mrs. George and Mrs. Charlotte Perkins; Longley, R.I.; Moreland, Wallace; Seckerson, Mrs. Howard; Stemmons, Mrs. Walter. Each of these people interviewed by Miss Keyes were associated with the University of Connecticut during the tenure of President Beach. The transcripts are wonderful recollections of life on the campus in the early part of this century. The files include original, edited, and corrected copies of the interviews.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Beach, Louise Crombie, d. 1924 -Art collections.; Beach, Charles Lewis, 1866-1933.; Brundage, A.J., Mrs.—Interviews.; Davis, I.G., Mrs.—Interviews.; Stemmons, Walter, Mrs.—Interviews.; Seckerson, H.A. (Harold Arnold), b. 1875 -Interviews.; Moreland, Wallace S. (Wallace Sheldon)—Interviews.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut. School of Home Economics.; Louise Crombie Beach Memorial Collection (Storrs, Conn.); American Home Economics Association.; University of Connecticut—Presidents.; Home economists—Connecticut.; Painting—Connecticut.; College presidents—Connecticut.; Trade and professional associations—United States.; Art—Study and teaching—Connecticut.; College presidents' spouses—Connecticut.; Home economics—Study and teaching—Connecticut.; Home economics—United States.; Home economics—Societies, etc.; Art—Exhibitions.; Art—Connecticut.; Universities and colleges—Connecticut.; Connecticut—Education—Universities and colleges.; Connecticut—Cultural affairs—Art.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Press releases.; School Records.; Audio cassettes.; Scrap-Books.; Interviews.; Oral Histories.
Occupations:
Educator.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Custodial History
Recent additions to the collection (not yet incorporated) have been donated by the Mansfield Historical Society, which had received the materials from members of Miss Keyes' family.
Acquisition Information
The Wilma Keyes Papers were donated to the Historical Manuscripts and Archives Division of the University Libraries over a period of several years in the early 1980s. Each group of records has been a small assortment of a variety of academic related materials. The largest portion of the collection was transferred to the Historical Manuscripts & Archives Division from the William Benton Museum of Art in August of 1987.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Academic Files, undated, 1938-1961
  - American Home Economics Association (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Art 130 Elementary Freehand Drawing (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Art 132 Introduction to Art (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Art 133 Drawing and Painting (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Art 135 Art Appreciation (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Art 230 History of Art (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Art 243 Craft Techniques (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Art 243 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Art 246 Advanced Design (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Art 248 Visual Expression (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Art 249 Textile Design (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Art at UConn...Present Trends, 1944-1945 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Art Club (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Art Courses, notes (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Art Workshop (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Bachelor of Science List, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Budget (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Cumulative Record of Professional Activities (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Curriculum
    - Committee Reports (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - Studies (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Home Economics Department Objectives (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Pamphlets (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - Newsletter (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - Papers, Addresses (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - Report of the Committee for the Correlation of Related Arts with Textiles and Clothing, 1938-1939 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
  - State Teaching Certificate Requirements (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - Women's Faculty Club (Box 1:, Folder 29)
- Series II: Correspondence and Notes, undated
  - Beach Collection (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - Beach Research Collection (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - Christmas Newsletters (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Oluf Nielson Memoirs (Box 1:, Folder 33)
- Series III: Publications, undated, 1926-1972
  - A History of the Connecticut Home Economics Association (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - The Connecticut Alumnus, 1971 June, December; 1972 June (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - Connecticut Home Economics Newsletter, 1926 December (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - Dedication of...Home Economics Building (Box 1:, Folder 37)
  - Fine Arts Magazine, vol. 5, no. 2 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - Home Economics News (Box 1:, Folder 39)
  - Home Economics Brochure, UConn (Box 1:, Folder 40)
  - The Inauguration of Homer Daniels Babbidge, Jr. (Box 1:, Folder 41)
  - The Louise Crombie Beach Memorial Collection Of Art (Box 1:, Folder 42)
  - Mr. Beach (Box 1:, Folder 43)
  - Newspaper Clippings, miscellaneous (Box 1:, Folder 44)
  - The Silver Convocation Honoring Dr. Albert Nels Jorgensen (Box 1:, Folder 45)
  - University of Connecticut Bulletin Biennial Report (Box 1:, Folder 46)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks, 1944-1962
  - Guest/Scrap Books from Exhibitions, 1944-1946, 1962 (Box 1:, Folder 47)
  - Loose Scrapbook pages (Box 1:, Folder 48)
  - A History of the Society of Connecticut Craftsmen (Box 1:, Folder 67)
- Series V: Tapes, Oral History, 1970s
  - Anderson (Box 2:, Folder 49)
  - Anderson/Passmore (Box 2:, Folder 50)
  - Brundage/Davis (Box 2:, Folder 51)
  - Griswold (Box 2:, Folder 52)
  - Longley, R.I. (Box 2:, Folder 53)
  - Mason/Keyes (Box 2:, Folder 54)
  - Seckerson/Larson (Box 2:, Folder 55)
  - Seckerson/Stemmons/Lamson/Perkins (Box 2:, Folder 56)
- Series VI: Transcripts, Oral History, 1970s
  - Anderson, Helen Stevens and Winifred Smith Passmore (Box 2:, Folder 57)
  - Belden, Robert Fitch (Box 2:, Folder 58)
  - Brundage, A.J. (Mrs.) and Mrs. I.G. Davis (Box 2:, Folder 59)
  - Fultz, Charlotte Dutch (Box 2:, Folder 60)
  - Griswold, Gladys Wheeler (Box 2:, Folder 61)
  - Lamson, George (Mrs.) and Mrs. Charles Perkins (Box 2:, Folder 62)
  - Longley, R.I. (Box 2:, Folder 63)
  - Moreland, Wallace (Box 2:, Folder 64)
  - Seckerson, Howard (Mrs.) (Box 2:, Folder 65)
  - Stemmons, Walter (Mrs.) (Box 2:, Folder 66)